Finding aid to the Parker-McCollester Family papers SSC.MS.00231
Sophia Smith Collection
Parker-McCollester Family papers
1764-2009
Sophia Smith Collection
Parker-McCollester Family
SSC.MS.00231
10 boxes (7.5 linear feet)
Civic leader; intellectual; teacher; lawyer; congressman; minister. Papers include diaries of Elizabeth Parker McCollester, 1878-1925, which record Smith College life, women's clubs, Claremont (NH), Detroit, and Medford (Mass.). There is also family correspondence, travel diaries, photographs, and memorabilia of various members of the family resided in New Hampshire.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections. Collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use. Fragile papers should not be photocopied.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Elizabeth von Klemperer and Parker Emerson in 1989, 2013, and 2016.
Biographical / Historical
The papers represent several generations of the Parker- McCollester family in New Hampshire. Lovisa Southgate of Bridgewater, VT, was the daughter of a textile mill owner who taught for several years before her marriage to Hosea W. Parker of Lempster, NH, the son of a subsistence farmer who went on to be a lawyer active as a Democrat in NH state politics, serving two terms in Congress. Their daughter was Lizzie Southgate Parker McCollester born in Claremont, NH 17 May 1865. She graduated from Stevens High School in Claremont in 1884 and received her A.B. from Smith College in 1888. The following year she married Lee McCollester, a Universalist minister and the young couple moved to Detroit where McCollester served as pastor in that city's Universalist Church. In Detroit Lizzie McCollester was a founder of the Twentieth Century Club; helped organize in the Michigan Smith College Club; and was a charter member of the Fine Arts Society of Detroit. In 1912 Lee McCollester became Dean of the Crane Theology School at Tufts College and the family then moved to Medford, Massachusetts. Lizzie McCollester continued to be active in her new home where her organizational skills were put to use in many settings including the Boston Smith College Club and the Medford Shakespeare Club. Lizzie Parker McCollester gave birth to three children, one of whom died in infancy. She died in Medford, Massachusetts of cancer 1 April 1928. Other individuals represented include Catherine McCollester Gallaher (Smith 1914), her husband Hugh Gallaher, and Elizabeth Gallaher von Klemperer (Smith 1944).
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Scope and Contents
Papers include diaries, family correspondence, travel diaries, photographs, and memorabilia of various members of the family resided in New Hampshire. The diaries kept by Elizabeth Parker McCollester from 1878 to 1925 (some gaps) are all "line-a-day"s. While there is little in the way of introspective prose, the diaries do record the activities of an involved club woman and include some description of Smith College life, Claremont (NH), Detroit, and Medford (Mass.) Each diary also includes a financial record in back and a few inserts including photographs and notes.
Claremont (N.H.)--History--19th century--Sources; Detroit (Mich.)--History--Sources; Massachusetts--History--20th century--Sources; Parker family; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; McCollester, Elizabeth Parker, 1865-1928; Tufts University--History--Sources; Parker, Hosea Washington; Parker, Louvisa C. Southgate; McCollester, Lee; Gallaher, Catherine McCollester; Gallaher, Hugh; von Klemperer, Elizabeth Gallaher; McCollester family; McCollester, Parker; McCollester, Dorothea de Forest Baldwin; Emerson, Ann Parker McCollester; diaries; photographs; Notes; Account books; correspondence; Sermons; Genealogies; Writings; Financial records; Legal documents; Speeches; Parker Family; McCollester Family; Parker, Hosea W., 1833-1922; Southgate, Caroline Lovisa, 1831-1904; Parker, Lizzie Southgate, 1865-1928; McCollester, Lee Sullivan, 1859-1943; Leigh, Mary Gallaher; Parker-McCollester Family; Emerson, Parker McCollester; von Klemperer, Elizabeth Gallaher; Emerson, Parker McCollester
- Parker-McCollester family papers including correspondence, diaries, photographs, publications and miscellaneous materials, 1764-2009; 1800-2009; 2013-S-0056; von Klemperer, Elizabeth Gallaher; 7 linear feet (7 boxes)
  - Transcripts of correspondence of Hosea W. Parker and Lovisa Southgate Parker, 1854-1861; 2013-S-0056 (Box 1)
  - Lee McCollester published and unpublished sermons and essays, 1890-1929; 2013-S-0056 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth von Klemperer and family correspondence and photographs, 1928-2009; 2013-S-0056 (Box 1)
  - Lizzie Parker McCollester correspondence, 2013-S-0056; Fragile (Box 1)
  - Lee and Lizzie Parker McCollester correspondence to family, 1888-1889; 2013-S-0056; Fragile (Box 1)
  - Lee McCollester and Lizzie Parker courtship letters, 1888-1889; 2013-S-0056; Fragile (Box 1)
  - Knight family correspondence annotated by Elizabeth von Klemperer, 1847-2005; 2013-S-0056 (Box 2)
  - Southgate family correspondence, memorabilia, financial records, 1820-1839; 2013-S-0056; "very fragile" per original box list (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth von Klemperer, "Ancestors and Genealogy.", undated; 2013-S-0056 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, diaries and other matrerials related to Sullivan, Sophia Knight and Lee McCollester, 1860-1869; 1910-1919; 2013-S-0056 (Box 2)
  - Sullivan and Sophia Knight McCollester correspondence, diaries, writings, 1847-1919; 2013-S-0056 (Box 3)
  - Financial documents, 1767-1774; 2013-S-0056 (Box 3)
  - Lee and Lizzie Parker McCollester letters to famiy, 1891-1908; 2013-S-0056 (Box 3)
  - Catherine McCollester Gallaher photo albums, Bride's Gift Book, passports, diaries, 1913-1975; 1913-1934; 2013-S-0056 (Box 3)
  - Photographs and other materials related to Hosea W. Parker House, Claremont, NH, 1888-2001; 2013-S-0056 (Box 4)
  - Catharine McCollester Gallaher correspondence to Hugh Gallaher, 1919-1924; 2013-S-0056 (Box 4)
  - Lee and Lizzie Parker McCollester correspondence, 1889-1922; 2013-S-0056 (Box 4)
  - Hosea W. and Lovisa Southgate Parker correspondence, diaries, speeches and related materials, 1850-1919; 2013-S-0056 (Box 5)
  - Lee Sullivan McCollester memoirs, diaries, account books, 1894-1939; undated; 2013-S-0056 (Box 6)
  - Catherine McCollester Gallaher diaries, photo album, correspondence and miscelaneous materials, 1893-1987; 2013-S-0056 (Box 7)
- Parker and Dorothea de Forest Baldwin McCollester correspondence, journals, family histories and related materials, 1882-2007; 2016-S-0093; Emerson, Parker McCollester; 3 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Parker McCollester correspondence related to birth, 1890; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester, "National Reporter.", 1905; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester Phillips Exeter, Tufts memorabilia, 1908; 1913; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester miscellaneous personal and business correspondence, 1909-1925; 1909-1952; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester correspondence to family, diary, memorabilia during World War service, 1918-1919; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester diary, expenses regarding European trip, 1938; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester correspondence, official documents, memorabilia from service around invasion of Normandy, 1944; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester notes regarding interviews and studies of the Marshall Plan, 1948; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding death of Parker McCollester, 1954; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester correspondence to Lee McCollester, 1913-1942; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Lee McCollester biographical materials, 1884; 1909; 1943; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Jessie Baldwin correspondence to Lizzie McCollester, 1922; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Glalaher and Klemens von Klemperer miscellaneous materials, 1948; 1953; 2000; 2016-S-0093 (Box 1)
  - Parker McCollester correspondence to parents from Phillips Exeter, 1907-1908; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester, "Miscellaneous War Papers and Correspondence, Word War I", 1918-1919; 2016-S-0093; Includes handwritten letter of recommendation from then Supreme Court Justice Louis Brandeis, McCollester's former boss at Brandeis, Dunbar & Nutter, April 25, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester personal and professional correspondence, 1937-1952; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester correspondence to wife and family, 1938; 1944; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester speeches and notes, 1945-1953; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester materials related to Russell Lecture, Tufts University, 1952; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester miscellaneous materials, 1945-1949; undated; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester obituaries and tributes, 1954; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Ann Parker McCollester Emerson memoir, 1999; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Dorothea de Forest Baldwin McCollester letters to mother, 1916; 1918; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Dorothea de Forest Baldwin McCollester letters to Parker McCollester, 1937; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Dorothea de Forest Baldwin McCollester concerts, opera and plays material, 1900 -1967; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - McCollester and Emerson family histories and genealogies, undated; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Family poems and song lyrics, 1924-1951; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Ann McCollester Emerson diaries, 1942-1944; 2001; 2007; 2016-S-0093 (Box 2)
  - Parker McCollester, "The Mother's Record", 1890-1896; 2016-S-0093 (Box 3)
  - Parker McCollester cash book and diaries, 1907-1917; 2016-S-0093 (Box 3)
  - Dorothea de Forest Baldwin McCollester journals and diaries, 1902-1906; 1909-1913; 1916; 1918; undated; 2016-S-0093 (Box 3)
  - Dorothea de Forest Baldwin McCollester weights and measures of Roger, Duncan and Ann, 1924-1939; 2016-S-0093 (Box 3)
  - Parker McCollester memoribiia, undated; 2016-S-0093 (Box 4)
  - Parker McCollester US Army citation for meritorious service, 1919; 2016-S-0093 (Box 4)
  - Parker McCollester portrait, 1921; 2016-S-0093 (Box 4)